Stephen Crane Collection Photographs
Stephen Crane Collection Photographs
1873-1899
1 linear ft.
Photographs of Crane as a child, young man (Syracuse University baseball team), in Greece, at Linson's studio; also a few photographs of Crane's parents, sister and wife and one of Crane's short-lived crush, the young Nellie Crouse. Formats include prints, negatives and glass plate negatives.
2764892
Biographical History
Stephen Crane (1871-1900) was an American novelist, poet and journalist. Crane's mother, Mary Helen Peck, was the daughter of George Peck, an American Methodist Episcopal clergyman, author, and President of Cazenovia Seminary in Madison County, New York. Crane attended but did not graduate from Lafayette College and Syracuse University before moving to New York City where he worked as a freelance journalist and writer. His first novel, Maggie: A Girl of the Streets, was published in 1893, followed in 1895 by the novel for which he is best known, The Red Badge of Courage. The latter, about a young soldier's initiation into the horrors and ironies of war set during the American Civil War, won great acclaim for its vividness and psychological depth.
Crane and Cora Stewart-Taylor, who would become his wife, moved to Sussex, England in 1897. The two worked together as war correspondents during the Greco-Turkish War of 1897, novelized in Crane's Active Service (1899) whose central character is a journalist covering the war. Crane died at age 28 of tuberculosis in Badenweiler, Baden, Germany.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Stephen Crane Collection Photographs contains photographs of American author and journalist Stephen Crane as a child, young man (Syracuse University baseball team), in Greece, and at the studio of portrait photographer Corwin Knapp Linson. There are also a few photographs of Crane's parents, sister and wife and one of a young woman named Nellie Crouse, for whom Crane had a short-lived passion. Formats include original photographs, original and copy negatives, and glass plate negatives.
Within the single box, glass plate negatives reside in a small box, prints are in a folder, and negatives are in mylar pages in a three-ring binder. In the inventory below, numbers preceding the negatives and prints refer to page numbers in the binder; numbers preceding glass plate negatives refer to the penciled numbers written on the paper covers of the negatives in the box.
Arrangement of the Collection
Roughly chronological.
Related Material
See also the
Stephen Crane Collection
. In addition, has many published Crane works and reference materials in its Rare Books holdings; please refer to for a complete listing. is also the repository of the papers of
George Peck
, Crane's maternal grandfather.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Crane, Cora, 1865 or 6-1910 -- Photographs.; Crane, Stephen, 1871-1900 -- Photographs.; Crouse, Nellie -- Photographs.; Linson, Corwin Knapp, b. 1864.; Syracuse University -- Baseball -- Photographs.; Photography -- Negatives.; Negatives (photographs); Photographs.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Original photographs in Box 2 are restricted due to condition. Researchers may use the reproductions in Box 1.
Inventory
- Negatives and prints
  - 01 S. Crane, approximately age 2, circa 1873; copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #1
  - 02 S. Crane, approximately age 2, circa 1873; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 03 Crane with Company B of the Battalion at Hudson River Inst., 1888-1889; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 04 Crane in Syracuse University baseball team uniform, close-up from team photo, spring 1891; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 05 Crane with SU baseball team, spring 1891; 2 original photos, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 06 Pendennis Club Crane, friends, skeletons, 1892; original photo and neg., 2 copy neg.s (Box 1)
  - 07 Pendennis Club Crane with head wrapped in towel smoking hookah, 1893; original photo, 4 copies retouched neg., before and after cleaning (Box 1)
  - 08 Pendennis Club photo of Crane with head wrapped in towel, hookah changed to a pipe, caption at bottom "The Pace of Youth", 1893; original photo, retouched copy neg (copy neg. also with #07) (Box 1)
  - 09 Crane with pipe, Linson photo, 1893; copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #2
  - 10 Crane with pipe, very blurred, Linson photo, 1893; copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #3
  - 11 Crane portrait, New York, Linson photo, 1893; copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #4
  - 12 Crane portrait, Linson photo, 1893 or 1894; 2-3 original photos, 1 old retouched neg., copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #5
  - 13 Crane on couch in Linson's studio (42W30), 1893; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 14 Crane portrait, Linson photo study for painting (#1), undated; original photo with caption "Photo by Corwin Knapp Linson 1894" at lower left, 2 copy neg.s of photo (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #6
  - 15 Crane portrait, Linson photo study for painting (#2), chin line pencilled in and right hand visible, 1894; original photo, 2 copy neg.s (Box 1)
  - 16 Crane and Linson seated on roof of Linson's studio, 1894; 2 original photos, 2 copy neg.s (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #7
  - 17 Crane and Linson standing on roof of studio, 1894; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #8
  - 18 Crane and Lucius Button on roof of Linson's studio, 1894; original photo, 2 copy neg.s (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #9
  - 19 Crane and Linson at Scranton coal mine, 1894; original neg., original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 20 Crane and Linson at Scranton coal mine, inscription at bottom, 1894; original photo, 3 copy neg.s (Box 1)
  - 21 Crane on horseback, Jacksonville, Florida, 1896; original photo, 2 copy neg.s (Box 1)
  - 22 S. Crane, early 1896; older 8x10 neg., copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 23 Crane in Greece (1a), 3/4 view, 1897; original photo, copy neg., copy photo from Schoberlin Collection credited to Newark Public Library (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #10
  - 24 Crane in Greece (1b) same as 1a except neg. made from framed photo, 1897; original framed photo, neg. made from photo (Box 1)
  - 25 Crane in Greece (2), side view, 1897; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #11
  - 26 Crane in Greece (3a) with John Bass, 1897; copy neg., older photo from Schoberlin Collection (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #12
  - 27 Crane in Greece (3b) with John Bass, same as 3a but neg. made from framed photo, 1897; original framed photo, 8x10 copy neg. made from photo, 4x5 copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 28 Crane in study at Brede Place, Sussex, England, 1899; original mounted photo, copy neg. from photo (Box 1)
  - 29 Crane at desk, undated; copy neg. (Box 1)
    See also glass plate negatives #13
  - 30 Agnes Crane (sister), undated; original photo from Schoberlin Collection, copy neg. from photo [original missing 1991] (Box 1)
  - 31 Cora Stewart Crane, undated; original photo, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 32 Cora Stewart Crane, caption "To Mable from Auntie Cora April '92" written on photo, 1892; original photo, older 8x10 neg., copy neg. from photo, older photo from Schoberlin Collection (Box 1)
  - 33 Cora Stewart Crane in Greece as Imogen Carter, 1897; original photo, 8x10 copy neg. from photo, 4x5 copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 34 Jonathan Townley Crane (father), facing right, circa 1875; original photo, 5x7 copy neg. from photo, 4x5 copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 35 Jonathan Townley Crane (father), facing left, circa 1875; original photo, copy neg. from photo (Box 1)
  - 36 Mary Helen Peck Crane (mother), 1889; older neg, copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 37 Nellie Crouse, with dog, 1895 or 1896; original (?) photo, older neg., copy neg. (Box 1)
  - 38 Claverack College and Hudson River Insitutute, with S. Crane inscription on back, undated; original photo from Schoberlin Collection, 2 copy neg.s from photo (front and back) (Box 1)
  - Originals of the above, 38 items (Box 2)
    Original photographs in Box 2 are restricted due to condition. Researchers are encouraged to use the reproductions in Box 1.
- Glass plate negatives
  - 01 S. Crane, approximately age 2, circa 1873 (Box 1)
  - 02 Crane with pipe, Linson photo, 1893 (Box 1)
  - 03 Crane with pipe, very blurred, Linson photo, 1893 (Box 1)
  - 04 Crane portrait, New York, Linson photo, 1893 (Box 1)
  - 05 Crane portrait, Linson photo, 1893 or 1894 (Box 1)
  - 06 Crane portrait, Linson photo study for painting (#1), undated (Box 1)
  - 07 Crane and Linson seated on roof of Linson's studio, 1894 (Box 1)
  - 08 Crane and Linson standing on roof of studio, 1894 (Box 1)
  - 09 Crane and Lucius Button on roof of Linson's studio, 1894 (Box 1)
  - 10 Crane in Greece (1a), 3/4 view, 1897 (Box 1)
  - 11 Crane in Greece (2), side view, 1897 (Box 1)
  - 12 Crane in Greece (3a) with John Bass, 1897 (Box 1)
  - 13 Crane at desk, undated (Box 1)